<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Open Data | Pezholio]]></title>
  <link href="http://pezholio.github.com/blog/categories/open-data/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://pezholio.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-04T17:58:54+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://pezholio.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Pezholio]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[pezholio@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Beginner's Guide to SPARQLing Linked Data (Part 1)]]></title>
    <link href="http://pezholio.github.com/2011/01/a-beginners-guide-to-sparqling-linked-data-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2011-01-14T14:00:59+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://pezholio.github.com/2011/01/a-beginners-guide-to-sparqling-linked-data-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>Regular readers of this blog will have seen that, over the past 12 months or so, I&#x2019;ve been banging on about linked data and SPARQL quite a bit, posting up example queries and the like, but with not much explanation about why I&#x2019;m doing what I&#x2019;m doing.</p>

<p>Thanks to the good folks at Talis and their offer of a <a href="http://www.talis.com/localgov/pr/">free linked data store for spending data</a>, I&#x2019;ve also got a nice little store of my own, and I thought it was high time I went back to basics and passed on what I&#x2019;ve learnt to other people.</p>

<h3>First, a bit of background</h3>

<p>The web, as most of us know it, is a network of <strong>documents</strong>, with each document having an individual URI to show its location on the web. With linked data, the web becomes an network of <strong>things</strong> with each thing having an individual URI to tell us more about it.</p>

<p>When talking about linked data, we talk about UR<strong>I</strong>s, rather than UR<strong>L</strong>s, as URLs refer the the location of a file, whereas URIs are identifiers for things, which could return any format.</p>

<p>An example of a URI is <a href="http://spending.lichfielddc.gov.uk/costcentre/waste-shared-service">http://spending.lichfielddc.gov.uk/costcentre/waste-shared-service</a> - when you access this via a web browser, the web browser asks for HTML and a web page giving information about this particular cost centre is returned. If you request this in any other way (say via the command line) and ask for RDF, you will get an <a href="http://spending.lichfielddc.gov.uk/costcentre/waste-shared-service.rdf">RDF representation of information about this cost centre</a> (web browsers filter out some of the XML, so it might be worth right clicking and selecting &#x201C;view source&#x201D; to see everything).</p>

<p>As well as identifying things, URIs also represent categories of things (called properties), the previous example therefore is an expenditure category, represented by the URI <a href="http://reference.data.gov.uk/def/payment#expenditureCategory">http://reference.data.gov.uk/def/payment#expenditureCategory</a>. To get all the properties being used for our spending dataset, we can do the following SPARQL query:</p>

<p><code>
SELECT DISTINCT ?o WHERE {?s a ?o}
</code></p>

<p><a href="http://api.talis.com/stores/lichfielddc-gov-uk/services/sparql?query=SELECT+DISTINCT+%3Fo+WHERE+%7B%3Fs+a+%3Fo%7D">See the results of this query</a></p>

<h3>SPARQL queries themselves</h3>

<p>SPARQL stands for <strong>S</strong>PARQL <strong>P</strong>rotocol and <strong>R</strong>DF <strong>Q</strong>uery <strong>L</strong>anguage and is a similar sort of idea to SQL (which is used in most databases both on and off the web). The main difference is that while SQL generally allows us read and write from and to a database (and therefore not particularly safe to give everyone access), SPARQL is built for public access, so is non-destructive in nature. SPARQL is, of course, still intended for developers and is just as powerful as SQL for querying datasets.</p>

<p>RDF datastores have a SPARQL endpoint, which is basically a fancy name for a place where you can make SPARQL queries. Our SPARQL endpoint is located at <a href="http://api.talis.com/stores/lichfielddc-gov-uk/services/sparql">http://api.talis.com/stores/lichfielddc-gov-uk/services/sparql</a> and we make SPARQL queries by posting a GET request to this URI in the format http://api.talis.com/stores/lichfielddc-gov-uk/services/sparql?query={SPARQL query goes here}, or by entering our query on a web-based form that posts to our endpoint. The form we will be using is located <a href="http://spending.lichfielddc.gov.uk/sparql">here</a>.</p>

<p>The first thing we do when writing a SPARQL query is define our prefixes. If you look at <a href="http://spending.lichfielddc.gov.uk/date/dec-2010.rdf">a snapshot of the data we&#x2019;ll be querying</a>, you&#x2019;ll see that most of the XML tags are written in the format prefix:type&gt; (RDF can be written in various formats, but I&#x2019;m using XML, which is not necessarily the best format, but that&#x2019;s a discussion for another day!). If you look at the top of the document (you might need to view source in your web browser) you&#x2019;ll see that all the prefixes are defined at the top as XML namespaces (for example &#x2018;xmlns:payment=&#x201D;http://reference.data.gov.uk/def/payment#&#x201D;&#x2019; means that the prefix &#x201C;payment&#x201D; will be shorthand for &#x201C;http://reference.data.gov.uk/def/payment#&#x201D;, so &#x201C;payment:reference&#x201D; actually refers to a URI, in this case &#x201C;http://reference.data.gov.uk/def/payment#reference&#x201D;). We can do this in a similar way in our SPARQL like so:</p>

<p><code>
PREFIX payment: http://reference.data.gov.uk/def/payment#
</code></p>

<p>There may be other prefixes too, and we do these a line at a time, for example:</p>

<p><code>
PREFIX payment: http://reference.data.gov.uk/def/payment#
PREFIX rdfs: http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#
PREFIX xsd: http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#
</code></p>

<p>The next thing to do is choose what data we want to return (in a similar way to an SQL SELECT query)</p>

<p><code>
SELECT ?payment WHERE {
</code></p>

<p>Here we&#x2019;re asking for one part of the dataset, which will be the URI which represents a particular payment. At this point, it doesn&#x2019;t matter what we call it, as we need to define this in the next bit of our query:</p>

<p><code>
?payment a payment:Payment .
</code></p>

<p>Here we&#x2019;re saying &#x201C;You know that thing I asked for in the SELECT part of the statement? That needs to be a http://reference.data.gov.uk/def/payment#Payment&#x201D;.</p>

<p>We could stop here, but we&#x2019;ll end up getting all the data back, which would take a long time, and probably not be very useful, so let&#x2019;s filter this by only asking for payments made to a particular supplier:</p>

<p><code>
?Payment payment:payee http://spending.lichfielddc.gov.uk/supplier/burntwood-road-sweepers-ltd
</code></p>

<p>Let&#x2019;s put it all together:</p>

<p><code>
PREFIX payment: http://reference.data.gov.uk/def/payment#
SELECT ?Payment WHERE {
  ?Payment a payment:Payment .
  ?Payment payment:payee http://spending.lichfielddc.gov.uk/supplier/burntwood-road-sweepers-ltd
}
</code></p>

<p><a href="http://api.talis.com/stores/lichfielddc-gov-uk/services/sparql?query=PREFIX+payment%3A+%3Chttp%3A%2F%2Freference.data.gov.uk%2Fdef%2Fpayment%23%3E%0D%0A%0D%0ASELECT+%3FPayment+WHERE+%7B%0D%0A++%3FPayment+a+payment%3APayment+.%0D%0A++%3FPayment+payment%3Apayee+%3Chttp%3A%2F%2Fspending.lichfielddc.gov.uk%2Fsupplier%2Fburntwood-road-sweepers-ltd%3E+.%0D%0A%7D+">See the results of the query</a>.</p>

<p>The query returns a list of URIs, if you copy and paste these into your browser, you&#x2019;ll see a web page about that payment. The list isn&#x2019;t very useful in itself, so let&#x2019;s ask for a bit more data.</p>

<p>We&#x2019;ll first modify the prefixes:</p>

<p><code>
PREFIX payment: http://reference.data.gov.uk/def/payment#
PREFIX rdfs: http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#
</code></p>

<p>Then the rest of the query:</p>

<p><code>
SELECT ?Payment ?label ?date {
  ?Payment a payment:Payment .
  ?Payment payment:payee http://spending.lichfielddc.gov.uk/supplier/burntwood-road-sweepers-ltd .
  ?Payment rdfs:label ?label .
  ?Payment payment:date ?date
}
</code></p>

<p><a href="http://api.talis.com/stores/lichfielddc-gov-uk/services/sparql?query=PREFIX+payment%3A+%3Chttp%3A%2F%2Freference.data.gov.uk%2Fdef%2Fpayment%23%3E%0D%0APREFIX+rdfs%3A+%3Chttp%3A%2F%2Fwww.w3.org%2F2000%2F01%2Frdf-schema%23%3E%0D%0A%0D%0ASELECT+%3FPayment+%3Flabel+%3Fdate+WHERE+%7B%0D%0A++%3FPayment+a+payment%3APayment+.%0D%0A++%3FPayment+payment%3Apayee+%3Chttp%3A%2F%2Fspending.lichfielddc.gov.uk%2Fsupplier%2Fbiffa-waste-services-ltd%3E+.%0D%0A++%3FPayment+rdfs%3Alabel+%3Flabel+.%0D%0A++%3FPayment+payment%3Adate+%3Fdate+.%0D%0A%7D+">See the results of this query</a>.</p>

<p>Hopefully you&#x2019;ll be able to see what&#x2019;s going on here, we&#x2019;re now asking for the label of the payment (rdfs:label) and also the date (Payment:date). In this dataset, the date is returned as a URI (i.e. <a href="http://reference.data.gov.uk/id/day/2010-04-26">http://reference.data.gov.uk/id/day/2010-04-26</a>), but we can also return the date&#x2019;s label in text form by adding the following:</p>

<p><code>
SELECT ?Payment ?label ?date **?datelabel** {
</code></p>

<p>&#x2026;snip</p>

<p><code>
?date rdfs:label ?datelabel .
</code></p>

<p>Here we&#x2019;re saying &#x201C;You know that date I asked for? I also want to see it&#x2019;s label, and I want to call it datelabel&#x201D;. The query now looks like this:</p>

<p><code>
PREFIX payment: http://reference.data.gov.uk/def/payment#
PREFIX rdfs: http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#
SELECT ?Payment ?label ?date ?datelabel {
?Payment a payment:Payment .
?Payment payment:payee http://spending.lichfielddc.gov.uk/supplier/burntwood-road-sweepers-ltd .
?Payment rdfs:label ?label .
?Payment payment:date ?date .
?date rdfs:label ?datelabel
}
</code></p>

<p><a href="http://api.talis.com/stores/lichfielddc-gov-uk/services/sparql?query=PREFIX+payment%3A+%3Chttp%3A%2F%2Freference.data.gov.uk%2Fdef%2Fpayment%23%3E%0D%0APREFIX+rdfs%3A+%3Chttp%3A%2F%2Fwww.w3.org%2F2000%2F01%2Frdf-schema%23%3E%0D%0A%0D%0ASELECT+%3FPayment+%3Flabel+%3Fdate+%3Fdatelabel+%7B%0D%0A%3FPayment+a+payment%3APayment+.%0D%0A%3FPayment+payment%3Apayee+%3Chttp%3A%2F%2Fspending.lichfielddc.gov.uk%2Fsupplier%2Fburntwood-road-sweepers-ltd%3E+.%0D%0A%3FPayment+rdfs%3Alabel+%3Flabel+.%0D%0A%3FPayment+payment%3Adate+%3Fdate+.%0D%0A%3Fdate+rdfs%3Alabel+%3Fdatelabel+.%0D%0A%7D">See the results of this query</a>.</p>

<p>This is all well and good, but we don&#x2019;t see any actual figures yet, which isn&#x2019;t very useful. Going back to the <a href="http://spending.lichfielddc.gov.uk/date/dec-2010.rdf">snapshot of data</a> I showed earlier, you can see that each payment has one or more expenditureLines, expressed as:</p>

<p><code>
payment:expenditureLine rdf:resource="http://spending.lichfielddc.gov.uk/spend/9178363"/
</code></p>

<p>If you look below each Payment, you&#x2019;ll see the expenditureLine(s) for the payment, e.g:</p>

<p><code>
payment:ExpenditureLine rdf:about="http://spending.lichfielddc.gov.uk/spend/9178363"
rdfs:labelPayment number 9178363/rdfs:label
payment:expenditureCategory rdf:resource="http://spending.lichfielddc.gov.uk/costcentre/waste-shared-service"/
payment:expenditureCategory rdf:resource="http://spending.lichfielddc.gov.uk/type/supplies-services"/
payment:expenditureCategory rdf:resource="http://spending.lichfielddc.gov.uk/subjective/compost-disposal-costs"/
payment:payment rdf:resource="http://spending.lichfielddc.gov.uk/invoice/16148"/
payment:netAmount rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#decimal"1855.88/payment:netAmount
qb:dataSet rdf:resource="http://spending.lichfielddc.gov.uk/dataset.rdf#2010-12-v1"/
/payment:ExpenditureLine
</code></p>

<p>We can get this information in a similar way to how we got the date labels, so if we want to get a net amount for each payment we can add:</p>

<p><code>
SELECT ?Payment **?line** ?label ?date ?datelabel **?amount** {
</code></p>

<p>&#x2026;snip</p>

<p><code>
?line payment:payment ?Payment .
?line payment:netAmount ?amount
</code></p>

<p>Here we&#x2019;re now asking for each line that has a payment that is equal to &#x201C;?Payment&#x201D; (i.e. the Payments we&#x2019;ve originally requested) and asking for their net amounts. The query now looks like this:</p>

<p><code>
PREFIX payment: http://reference.data.gov.uk/def/payment#
PREFIX rdfs: http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#
SELECT ?Payment ?line ?label ?date ?datelabel ?amount {
?Payment a payment:Payment .
?Payment payment:payee http://spending.lichfielddc.gov.uk/supplier/burntwood-road-sweepers-ltd .
?Payment rdfs:label ?label .
?Payment payment:date ?date .
?date rdfs:label ?datelabel .
?line payment:payment ?Payment .
?line payment:netAmount ?amount
}
</code></p>

<p><a href="http://api.talis.com/stores/lichfielddc-gov-uk/services/sparql?query=PREFIX+payment%3A+%3Chttp%3A%2F%2Freference.data.gov.uk%2Fdef%2Fpayment%23%3E%0D%0APREFIX+rdfs%3A+%3Chttp%3A%2F%2Fwww.w3.org%2F2000%2F01%2Frdf-schema%23%3E%0D%0A%0D%0ASELECT+%3FPayment+%3Fline+%3Flabel+%3Fdate+%3Fdatelabel+%3Famount+%7B%0D%0A%3FPayment+a+payment%3APayment+.%0D%0A%3FPayment+payment%3Apayee+%3Chttp%3A%2F%2Fspending.lichfielddc.gov.uk%2Fsupplier%2Fburntwood-road-sweepers-ltd%3E+.%0D%0A%3FPayment+rdfs%3Alabel+%3Flabel+.%0D%0A%3FPayment+payment%3Adate+%3Fdate+.%0D%0A%3Fdate+rdfs%3Alabel+%3Fdatelabel+.%0D%0A%3Fline+payment%3Apayment+%3FPayment+.%0D%0A%3Fline+payment%3AnetAmount+%3Famount+.%0D%0A%7D">See the results of this query</a>.</p>

<p>Which seems like a pretty neat place to leave it now. Feel free to have a play with the stuff I&#x2019;ve gone thorough so far, and ask any questions in the comments. I don&#x2019;t claim to have all the answers, and I may have made some incorrect assumptions, so please feel free to put me right too!</p>

<p>Stay tuned for part 2, where I&#x2019;ll cover filters and other cool things.</p>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spending Data - Beyond the CSV]]></title>
    <link href="http://pezholio.github.com/2011/01/spending-data-beyond-the-csv/"/>
    <updated>2011-01-14T10:00:51+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://pezholio.github.com/2011/01/spending-data-beyond-the-csv</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p><img src="http://www.pezholio.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/csv.png" alt="">It&#x2019;s been a while since my <a href="http://www.pezholio.co.uk/2010/08/local-spending-data-a-few-ideas/">last post about local spending data</a>, and, since then, our finance team have been busy beavering away behind the scenes to get our own spending data out of the council&#x2019;s finance systems.</p>

<p>However, from the outset, I was really pleased that both our finance people and our chief exec wanted to go beyond just whacking a CSV (or worse, a PDF) on the internet and show our commitment to transparency by putting the data on the web in an easy, human readable format.</p>

<p>Armed with a few CSVs, a Macbook Pro and some server space, I was put to task, and the <a href="http://spending.lichfielddc.gov.uk/">the results can be seen here</a>. Users can navigate by the various parts of the cost code (called &#x201C;Department&#x201D;, &#x201C;Type&#x201D; and &#x201C;Subject&#x201D;), as well as by month and supplier.</p>

<p>As well as human readable formats, almost every view of the data has an XML, JSON, CSV and RDF equivalent, achieved either by putting the relevant extension on the end, or through <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Content_negotiation">content negotiation</a>.</p>

<p>The user interface had been heavily influenced by <a href="http://openlylocal.com/councils/spending">OpenlyLocal</a> (after all, if it ain&#x2019;t broke, why fix it?) and, as well as feeding our data in to OpenlyLocal, we also take a little bit away. When data is imported into OpenlyLocal, the system does some clever data matching to match company names to real life entities on <a href="http://opencorporates.com/">Open Corporates</a>. We have a batch job that takes that information and puts it on our spending system - <a href="http://spending.lichfielddc.gov.uk/supplier/p-casey-land-reclamation-ltd.html">you can see an example here</a>. This is an example of how open data cuts both ways, by sharing our data, we can improve it.</p>

<p>Also, thanks to the wonderful people at <a href="http://www.talis.com/">Talis</a>, we have our RDF data in a triple store, so it can be queried, both through SPARQL queries and a free text search, making the data even more useful from the off. I&#x2019;m hoping to put together a tutorial in SPARQL soon, both here and on the Lichfield District Council website, which should hopefully demystify the process a bit more.</p>

<p>Finally, I&#x2019;m hoping to open source the code (once it&#x2019;s tidied up a bit), so of you&#x2019;re from a local authority and want to make your spending data a little more clear to Joe Public, then you can benefit from my work too!</p>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Grit Bins - Your Help Needed!]]></title>
    <link href="http://pezholio.github.com/2010/11/grit-bins-your-help-needed/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-12T10:28:36+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://pezholio.github.com/2010/11/grit-bins-your-help-needed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>During the <a href="http://lichhack.eventbrite.com/">Lichfield Hacks and Hackers day</a> yesterday (bigger blog post to come on that later) - I was gifted a list of <a href="https://spreadsheets.google.com/ccc?key=0As1cSxPJOFWldEpxNDZady1aUmhIVTFXUjdjZHJ1M1E&amp;hl=en">grit bins in Lichfield District</a>, I got very excited about this, but my excitement was quickly dampened when I realised that there was no geographical data in the list, just road names and a vague location.</p>

<p>However, I then thought &#x2018;not to worry, I can just ask people who live nearby to geolocate them on their phones and add them to a Google Doc&#x2019;, I asked a <a href="http://twitter.com/robthedog">@robthedog</a> (who lives in a village north of the district) if he could do a few when he got home, his reply was &#x2018;I can do one now&#x2019;:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.pezholio.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2010/11/gritbin-300x158.png" alt="Grit Bin on Google Street View"></p>

<p>Of course! Google Street view! This is where you lot come in. I&#x2019;m going to crowdsource the location of these grit bins (I&#x2019;ve <a href="https://spreadsheets.google.com/ccc?key=0As1cSxPJOFWldEpxNDZady1aUmhIVTFXUjdjZHJ1M1E&amp;hl=en#gid=0">already done a few myself</a>) - to help, all you need to do is follow a few simple steps:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Open up <a href="https://spreadsheets.google.com/ccc?key=0As1cSxPJOFWldEpxNDZady1aUmhIVTFXUjdjZHJ1M1E&amp;hl=en#gid=0">this Google document</a></p></li>
<li><p>Drag <a href="javascript:void(prompt('',gApplication.getMap(">this bookmarklet to your browser&#x2019;s toolbar</a>.getCenter()));)</p></li>
<li><p>Open up <a href="http://maps.google.co.uk">Google Maps</a> and search for a road name and town / village which doesn&#x2019;t have a lat/lng yet</p></li>
<li><p>Drag the little yellow street view man (<a href="http://www.pezholio.co.uk/?attachment_id=405">this guy</a>) to the map and have a look round Street View for the grit bin</p></li>
<li><p>Once you&#x2019;re right by it - zoom out of Street View and click the bookmarklet - a window will pop up with the lat/lng - you can then copy and paste it and enter it into the Google doc!</p></li>
</ol>


<p>It&#x2019;s that simple! If you could do just a couple, I&#x2019;ll be forever in your debt (I might buy you a pint if I see you in the flesh too!)</p>

<p>Once it&#x2019;s done, I&#x2019;ll be able to build a handy map of grit bins in the area and hopefully save a few slips and falls (as well as a few costly calls to our contact centre!). There&#x2019;s 87of them, and, as I&#x2019;ve already done 10, it should be long before I&#x2019;ve got them all.</p>

<p>Thanks again, you lovely people you!</p>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Steps to Councils Publishing Their Own Linked Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://pezholio.github.com/2010/09/council-linked-data/"/>
    <updated>2010-09-06T12:17:33+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://pezholio.github.com/2010/09/council-linked-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>On Friday, I toddled along to London for a bit of a chat about local spending data, organised by <a href="http://www.legsb.gov.uk/Home.aspx">LeGSB</a>, the local government e-Standards body. In particular we looked at how councils can publish their spending data in a linked data format. It was an interesting day, and much of the work seems to have already been done by folks much cleverer than myself.</p>

<p>However, at the end of the day, Paul Davidson (the Director of Standards at LeGSB) raised an interesting topic. At the moment, much of the <em>describing</em> of councils in the linked data world seems to be done by external bodies, such as <a href="http://statistics.data.gov.uk">The Office for National Statistics</a> and <a href="http://data.ordnancesurvey.co.uk">Ordnance Survey</a>, and often, this isn&#x2019;t always the best fit, with the data referring to geographical regions, rather than councils themselves.</p>

<p>Paul then made the point that really, it should be the councils themselves that describe who they are, rather than some arbitrary body, after all, there is no one better placed to know about the council than the council themselves! We then talked very briefly about the possibility of councils minting their own URIs and publishing some RDF with some information about themselves (such as contact details etc). Other organisations and people can then use these URIs to refer to the councils in their data.</p>

<p>I&#x2019;ve been mulling this over over the weekend, and I fired off an email this morning suggesting that, rather than publishing a page of RDF, people simply add data to their council homepages, either as RDFa or metadata (although I&#x2019;m not sure how you&#x2019;d do the latter!). People could then use their council homepage URLs as URIs (perhaps with #id at the end of the URI, to make the URI for the council different to the one for the page).</p>

<p>With this in mind I&#x2019;ve knocked up a sample dataset for Lichfield District Council using various ontologies from around the linked data web (including FOAF, vCard, Chris Taggart&#x2019;s Openly Local ontology and a bit of the <a href="http://www.epimorphics.com/public/vocabulary/org.html">Organizational (sic) Ontology</a>). I&#x2019;ve also <a href="http://sameas.org/">sameAs</a>ed to the <a href="http://statistics.data.gov.uk/">National Statistics Dataset</a>, <a href="http://openlylocal.com/">Openly Local</a> and <a href="http://openlylocal.com/">DBpedia</a>:</p>

<p>`
?xml version=&#x201D;1.0&#x201D;?&gt;
rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf=&#x201D;http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#&#x201D;
  xmlns:skos=&#x201D;http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#&#x201D;
  xmlns:rdfs=&#x201D;http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#&#x201D;
  xmlns:owl=&#x201D;http://www.w3.org/2002/07/owl#&#x201D;
  xmlns:foaf=&#x201D;http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/&#x201D;
  xmlns:dct=&#x201D;http://purl.org/dc/terms/&#x201D;
  xmlns:vcard=&#x201D;http://www.w3.org/2006/vcard/ns#&#x201D;
  xmlns:administrative-geography=&#x201D;http://statistics.data.gov.uk/def/administrative-geography/&#x201D;
  xmlns:openlylocal=&#x201D;http://openlylocal.com/info/vocab#&#x201D;
  xmlns:org=&#x201D;http://www.w3.org/ns/org#&#x201D;&gt;
rdf:Description rdf:about=&#x201D;http://www.lichfielddc.gov.uk/#id&#x201D;&gt;</p>

<pre><code>    rdfs:labelLichfield District Council/rdfs:label 
    vcard:organisation-nameLichfield District Council/vcard:organisation-name 
    rdf:type rdf:resource="http://openlylocal.com/info/vocab#DistrictAuthority"/ 
    rdf:type rdf:resource="http://www.w3.org/ns/org#FormalOrganization"/ 
    skos:notation rdf:datatype="http://statistics.data.gov.uk/def/administrative-geography//StandardCode"41UD/skos:notation
    foaf:mboxmailto:enquiries@lichfielddc.gov.uk/foaf:mbox 
    foaf:homepage rdf:resource="http://www.lichfielddc.gov.uk"/ 
    foaf:phone rdf:resource="tel:+44-1543-308999"/ 
foaf:holdsAccount 
  foaf:OnlineAccount rdf:about="http://twitter.com/Lichfield_DC" 
    foaf:accountServiceHomepage rdf:resource="http://twitter.com/"/ 
    foaf:accountNameLichfield_DC/foaf:accountName 
  /foaf:OnlineAccount 
/foaf:holdsAccount 
foaf:holdsAccount 
  foaf:OnlineAccount rdf:about="http://www.facebook.com/lichfielddc" 
    foaf:accountServiceHomepage rdf:resource="http://www.facebook.com/"/ 
    foaf:accountNameLichfield District Council/foaf:accountName 
  /foaf:OnlineAccount 
/foaf:holdsAccount 
vcard:ADR rdf:parseType="Resource" 
  vcard:ExtaddDistrict Council House, Frog Lane, Lichfield WS13 6YY/vcard:Extadd 
  vcard:CountryEngland/vcard:Country 
  vcard:postal-code rdf:resource="http://www.uk-postcodes.com/postcode/WS136YY.rdf" / 
/vcard:ADR 
    administrative-geography:coverage rdf:resource="http://data.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/id/7000000000014797"/ 
    owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://statistics.data.gov.uk/doc/local-authority/41UD"/ 
    owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://openlylocal.com/councils/156.rdf"/ 
    owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Lichfield_%28district%29"/ 
</code></pre>

<p>/rdf:Description&gt;
/rdf:RDF&gt;
`</p>

<p>It&#x2019;s not perfect, but it&#x2019;s a start, there&#x2019;s 24 triples there and I&#x2019;m sure there could be more. Only problem is, I&#x2019;m not a linked data expert, so I&#x2019;m looking for a bit of feedback both on what I&#x2019;ve done, but also what I could add - For example, I could add the chief executive and leader of the council - but I&#x2019;m not sure how I&#x2019;d do it!</p>

<p>Feedback from non-linked data experts is welcome too - especially those at the coal face of local gov - if there was a step by step guide to doing this, could you do it? (i.e. have you got access to add metadata to your homepage) and, more importantly, would you do it?</p>

<p><strong>UPDATE</strong> I&#x2019;ve now published the final(ish) version at <a href="http://www.lichfielddc.gov.uk/lichfield.rdf">http://www.lichfielddc.gov.uk/lichfield.rdf</a>, with a rel=&#x2019;alternate&#x2019; meta link on the Lichfield homepage. I&#x2019;ve also reused the reference.data.gov.uk ontology to show the councils CEO, leader etc, together with a bit of FOAF for their contact details.</p>

<p>Thanks to Jeni Tennison, Leigh Dodds and Dave Reynolds for helping me to get this far, and hopefully we can encourage more councils to do the same!</p>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Local Spending Data Brain Splurge]]></title>
    <link href="http://pezholio.github.com/2010/08/local-spending-data-a-few-ideas/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-02T14:40:49+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://pezholio.github.com/2010/08/local-spending-data-a-few-ideas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>Today I was at a &#x2018;quick and dirty&#x2019; local spending data workshop at Birmingham City Council&#x2019;s newly refurbished offices on Lancaster Circus. There&#x2019;ll be more detailed info to come on the <a href="http://www.communities.idea.gov.uk/c/3916997/home.do">Local Open Data Community</a> (login required), but I just wanted to blog a few of my thoughts post the meeting.</p>

<p>There was a lot of talk about what other councils have done (such as Windsor and Maidenhead, Barnet, Islington etc), and it was agreed that there was a lot of difference in how the data was presented, Paul Davidson also talked about some of the work that the <a href="http://www.legsb.gov.uk/">Local eGovernment Standards Body</a> had done regarding getting spending data out there in a linked data format. There did seem to be a bit of resistance to the linked data approach, mainly because agreeing standards seems to be a long, drawn out process, which is counter to the JFDI approach of publishing local data.</p>

<p>However, while I am a fan of the possibilities of linked data, I also recognise that there are difficulties in both publishing the data and also working with it. For example, I think it&#x2019;s unrealistic to expect every local authority to maintain a triple store to publish their spending data. As we learned from the local elections project, often local authorities don&#x2019;t even have people who are competent in HTML, let alone RDF, SPARQL etc.</p>

<p>Therefore, I think the way forward is a centralised approach, with authorities publishing CSVs in a standard format on their website and some kind of system picking up these CSVs (say, on a monthly basis) and converting this data to a linked data format (as well as publishing in vanilla XML, JSON and CSV format).</p>

<p>The great thing about the linked data approach is it will mean that each item of spending can have its own URI - e.g.</p>

<p><code>http://localspending.data.gov.uk/41UD/12345</code></p>

<p>(The first part of the URI would be the SNAC code for the authority, and then the second part of the URI would be the internal reference number)</p>

<p>As well as having a human-readable summary of the data (together with links to the actual data in RDF, XML, CSV and JSON), there would be a comments box (similar to <a href="http://twitter.com/adrianshort">Adrian Short&#x2019;s</a> fantastic <a href="http://armchairauditor.co.uk/">Armchair Auditor</a>), as well as the ability to ask any questions about an item of expenditure - the answers to these questions would then be automatically published next to the item of spend (hopefully helping to cut down on multiple FOI requests).</p>

<p>While this may be a bit of a pie in the sky idea, I do feel that there does need to be some kind of effort on the part of central government to help move this project along, as we&#x2019;ve seen already (naming no names!) some authorities have got it drastically wrong, and while there is definitely mileage in the &#x2018;just get it out there&#x2019; approach, I think if we&#x2019;re going to end up with something <em>really</em> useful (for both members of the public and local authorities), we need to get the data in one place.</p>

<p>Thoughts?</p>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
